[SPEAKER_01]: So, I've gathered some questions in terms of vinaya precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keeping the precepts or vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes people take the precepts because of circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, if the circumstances change, so does their precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And others take it on because they understand that it is beneficial regardless of circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, will both types of people be able to attain purity in terms of virtue, purity of mind, purity of view, resulting in freedom from suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it needs to be taken rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because one person is keeping the precepts, he's keeping the vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Duty circumstances, but for 50 years, doesn't really step out of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's meritorious, as I would have said.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not engaging with sensuality the way you would if you don't keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in and of itself, yeah, that does not result in mind turning away from sensuality, gaining an insight into the nature of non-ownership and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: That you need to keep the precepts rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that, we spoke about it, that keeping the precepts, it's basically whether you keep them, where the responsibility for the precepts is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what determines whether you keep them rightly or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, taking the precepts as a result of a tradition, culture, external values, and that, oh, it must be done because of that, means that's where the responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on this level of external acts.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why the mind is still bound with them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure, there are better acts than non-precepts, but... but if you recognize, no, no, no, I keep the precepts, because I choose to do so, because I want to train my mind, because of the weight of the tradition of the culture, that then brings it much closer to home, and it's harder to keep the precepts that way, because you realize, I can choose to not keep them.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on me.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no external authority or criteria or weight.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just... it's on me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I can...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can do it or not do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you feel that, oh, so then why am I doing it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So feeling the keeping of the precepts on that level, with that responsibility, and not breaking them on that level, with that responsibility,
[SPEAKER_02]: A person who takes them responsibly, or chooses to take on the precepts, sees where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, already they see I'm responsible for my mind being depressed, my mind being unhappy.
[SPEAKER_01]: What can I do about it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, sure, they can.
[SPEAKER_02]: They could, they could be seeing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to take on the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is, that is the only sort of right beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see that a direct
[SPEAKER_02]: Possibility that... Or at least have faith that there is a direct possibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you don't then mask the precepts and I do it just because we all agreed to do it and I'm fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: As long as I stick to our external agreement, I'm fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't have to think about anything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't have to reveal my intentions further.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm meeting the requirements.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm following the form.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm blameless.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's like, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're blameless if
[SPEAKER_02]: Your intentions are not rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in order to start revealing your intentions, you need to start keeping the precepts on that intentional level every single time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, I'm abstaining from breaking the precepts, I'm abstaining from sensual acts, acts of carelessness or anger, because I choose to do so, because I want to train my mind, not because...
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, then, you wouldn't be bothered if, say, we... well, we agreed to keep this precept and now you are not... you're just going doing your own thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't affect me.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not my problem, because I'm not defined by the group think nor group action.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm defined by my own intentions every single time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, you're probably less likely to, I mean, put the responsibility for, like, your
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's kind of helpful to be in a community of people who keep precepts, but the danger there is they're relying on the community for you keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's helpful to be in a community that keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, not necessarily helpful to be in a community that keep the precepts, but that never really points at where the, you know, responsibility should be and teaches you what you need to know.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're in community that keeps the precepts due to the external circumstances and the authority, and that's all they do, and then, when it comes to practice, the views are like here and there, and nothing brings you back to take on responsibility for those precepts, that's not helpful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, you're going to proliferate even more, because I'm sure many of the ascetics and brahmins in the suttas were virtuous in terms of the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, they were extremely, you know, like victims of extremely wrong views that the Buddha himself, like, you know, quite harshly mocked or dismissed or dismantled.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, many of them were probably quite, quite restrained in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: So...
[SPEAKER_02]: That, see, if somebody joins that sort of community whereby you would be restrained, but then with all these views that do not reveal the responsibility or undo it, just add further to it, well, that would be even harder to undo now than before.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you go along with it, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could be irresponsible in that context.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it always remains possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can always turn around.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's going to be factually harder, because now you are accumulating these further views on account of already that non-responsibility of your precepts and the virtue.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're in a community that keeps the precepts and then keeps teaching you how to take the responsibility for it and not rely on the community,
[SPEAKER_02]: And recognize your own intentions and the the roots of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's like, okay, now, see, the precepts have been taken.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if they haven't been taken rightly, now they've resulted in greater perspective that it's making you take it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will say, come and dwell restrained by this.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is the virtue, the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: And person starts doing it rightly, okay, now God sends those, now increase, okay, there's a... now be mindful with all the instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there is a sutta that says the danger of, like, relying on another person, like you, the danger of you, your precept, your practice, being reliant...
[SPEAKER_02]: Your well-being, yeah, your equilibrium.
[SPEAKER_02]: ...on someone else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone else doing that same stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that person, that monk, does, all of a sudden, changes and does a defiled act,
[SPEAKER_01]: And the saṅgha, yeah, he has to disrobe or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or my faith, or my inspiration.
[SPEAKER_02]: Was it the acrobats?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that too.
[SPEAKER_02]: One on the... standing on each other's shoulders.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, oh, you look after me, I look after you.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was like, no, no, actually, the safest will be if you look after yourself and I look after myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we're both going to be in sync.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another question is, I am afraid of breaking vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: I obsess over the minor details.
[SPEAKER_01]: And having now read that the Buddha, in his last instructions, said to the monks, after I am gone, the saṅgha, if it wants, may abolish the lesser and minor training rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it seems that I have been obsessing over things which are not important.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I should obsess over what is important, but I don't know which guidelines to now obsess over.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the Buddha himself says the minor, lesser training rules can be abolished, if you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, he's saying it's not that important.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you have to accept the fact that there is fear in your mind, on account of which you're obsessing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then not act out of fear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Accept it and endure it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, there are all these rules.
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I breaking?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'm afraid.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm doubtful.
[SPEAKER_02]: It feels unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I keep acting towards re-clarifying and rehashing all these rules and permutations, so then I can remove the doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why you're afraid, and that's why you're in doubt, and that's why you're not benefiting from keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to recognize that, and it's like, yeah, but I'm not breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind is making you think, and rehash, and recheck, and go into minor details.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha himself said, you could abolish all the minor and lesser rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just keep the main parājikas, and saṅgha disasters, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: That terrifies me now, because you basically... now that doubt that I've been feeding through trying to redefine and rehash the same answers over and over again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's... because it was never there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you need to stop acting out of the doubt, trying to get rid of it through, you know, revisiting the text and reclarifying what you already know, and accept the fact that you already know what the precepts are,
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not breaking them, and the mind is being irrational, and resisting, and trying to make you act towards it, and overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you have to endure that and not act.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because as that sutta says, when the Buddha's... in the Parinibbāna Sutta, when he's passing away, and he says... he doesn't clarify which are the minor rules that you can abolish.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that... but I think it's great, because it does leave responsibility on each person.
[SPEAKER_02]: After we passed away, Ananda reported it, and then all these arahants were like, guessing, or rather, suggesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, okay, well, I think, okay, I think that we can, we can abandon everything except the four grave offenses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then another arahant said, no, no, I think we can abandon everything except the four grave offenses and saṅgha disasses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then somebody says, well, let's include this, let's not include that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But generally, he was like, oh, just, just, just,
[SPEAKER_02]: Wipe all of it, except the four big parājikas, because that's enough for the training, from where they...
[SPEAKER_02]: They were arahants, factually.
[SPEAKER_02]: It wasn't just they were trying to get rid of the rules, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: They knew what was valuable for the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's kind of... And then, obviously, they said, well, let's not, for now at least, let's not abolish any of it, because the Buddha just passed away.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are many people that already know our rules, and they'll say, look, as soon as the teacher died, they are kind of dismissing his training.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there was a factual kind of reason back then, because the Buddha did just pass away and everybody was aware of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But today, you can use it, like, just even for yourself to reflect and kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so if they're like these arahants, they said...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, they were no Vinaya to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: When monks started practicing, they knew what to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: They knew what not to do, anything rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: But as things started, you know, as things were becoming more diluted, things were proliferating, and then certain rules needed to be defined, just certain criteria to remind you of where not to
[SPEAKER_02]: But yeah, so it's like, whether... and if you are acting out of a mind of doubt, even if you had just one rule, you could become irrational about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let alone if you have many more.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the point is that you are feeding that mind of doubt, that it's making you even more afraid of breaking, even more of this, even when you're not breaking it, because you keep trying to get rid of the discomfort of the doubt, through justifications of the external authority, the text, the tradition.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, please, Ajahn, tell me I'm not wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now I'm not wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are wrong, even if he told you you're not wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're wrong because you acted out of doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you still feel.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why you're still bound by those external things that are kind of covering up your own responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need the external authority, clarification, the text, the letter, to make you feel safe.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not where the safety comes from.
[SPEAKER_02]: Safety comes from not being moved by unsafety.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by doubt, which is unsafe.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fear is unsafe.
[SPEAKER_02]: I must clarify, so I'm safe.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you will remain unsafe.
[SPEAKER_02]: I must not act out of it, so that I can become safe.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, I don't need the tradition, or the texts, or even the Buddha himself.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what it says, like, in the suttas, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are your own guide now, when you get the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't even need Buddha's input.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, it's valuable to have it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would speed up your progress, but it's not necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's an advice of seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, where's the fault?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is the fault in this
[SPEAKER_02]: The hundredth, sort of, and fiftieth permutation of this letter?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fault is in the intention of greed, ill-will, distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the fault.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, see the danger in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot break any rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can... you can... you can, externally, not break any rules, but still act out of greed... Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's exactly what happens when the responsibility...
[SPEAKER_02]: When the responsibility is on the tradition or the community, there is no
[SPEAKER_02]: Revealing of your own intentions.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's when you start having all these loopholes in vinaya.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I can do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Revealing of the faults.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Revealing of the faults, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, I don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no revealing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of the...
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_02]: The slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might be revealing the... what you think faults are.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not really the faults that pertain to gradual training.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point what I was going to say was, you... if... when the responsibility is projected on the tradition, then, you're not seeing your intentions, which means now, anything that's not defined, oh, I can do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, see, the rule defines like this, which means this is allowable, because it hasn't been...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're already not having a context on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, because you think... when...
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you think that what you should or shouldn't do is defined by the letter, not by your intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll be doing things that are unsuitable, but are not necessarily explicitly forbidden by the letter or the culture or the tradition.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you will...
[SPEAKER_02]: Develop, like, even worse, this kind of discrepancy of that existential level, whereby you think you are pure, because, look, I'm blameless, I do everything right, while at the same time, you're actually more impure, because of your views, and because of further masking away of your own intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what should, as this question says, what should the person obsess over?
[SPEAKER_02]: Slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_02]: Slightest fault of acting out of hindrances, acting out of greed, aversion, distraction, doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the fault.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fault is you're trying to get rid of the pain of doubt through
[SPEAKER_02]: Placing the authority on the external things of tradition, books, definitions, and so on, senior monks, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way you can do something unwholesome, is to act out of unwholesome intentions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you might even break minor rules by mistake or, you know, just circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you act out of unwholesome intentions... Yeah, that's not a fault.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fault is when you act out of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even, you know, within the vinaya, within the precepts, that is still the fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the vinaya, there are so many rules which are predicated on the intention behind it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, those are the ones that matter, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, there's so many rules that are kind of circumstantial and, like, you know, simply not... you can't even... you can't even fathom how they would be applicable or something, because the circumstances have changed so much.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then you have the rules that, yeah, if the intention is like this, that's why it's an offense.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're already projected on the level of external culture, authority, tradition, for the definition of my rules, means that whole factor of intention, determining whether it's an offense or not, becomes invisible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you read that, oh, well, if you have intention rooted in lust, then it's an offense.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it wasn't rooted in lust, it wasn't an offense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, but was I, was I not?
[SPEAKER_02]: What book can it tell me whether my intention... Can you tell me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you... Can this community tell me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Please tell me, because... And then you realize, oh, you can't solve that doubt in that manner, because intention cannot be found in external authority.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do you do then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you ignore the factor of intention and start creating own rules within your own tradition in the culture.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would then prevent even a possibility of doubting my own intentions.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that takes you even further away from where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doubting your intentions is good.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's unpleasant, but it's useful.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it can actually reveal where the real problem is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You trying to get through the discomfort of the doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: You acting out of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: You not being able to remain unmoved, even when you know... No, my intention was good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but still... And you get perturbed, because the mind is undeveloped, and now you start acting towards it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you ignore what you know, and start trying to just irrationally get rid of the pain of the doubt that... Well, but wait, maybe if...
[SPEAKER_02]: There's always maybe if.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you're the one who has to draw a line, and then not cross it, through acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how then the mind will calm down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's another related question, I don't know if... in terms of assumption to virtue and duty or attachment to virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the question is, what exactly is the assumption there?
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's, I think, this assumption that this virtue and duty in itself will result in safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person can...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not going to do what I want to do anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just going to follow this community, these rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm blameless and I'm safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: And forget about myself, which means I am uprooting sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just following the rules of the community and doing what the rules are, thus no self, completely humble and purified.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I just stick to these prescribed rules of this particular community...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's basically exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Still finding safety in the external form.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's... ignoring the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You kind of block yourself in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's worse, in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you are adopting these views now, that are sheltering you even more than before.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it will be harder for you to give them up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it will be then... you have to experience that non-safety twice as much as you would have otherwise, if you didn't go down that rabbit hole of masking responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you, as I say, in the Buddhist monastic context, you have so many different types of Buddhism, and if there's another group of Buddhist monastics that do something slightly different, it's a kind of threat to your...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, I guess, schisms can arise, because, yeah, I'm attached to my community.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's why it almost happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm attached to my assumed safety, or the thing that gives me safety, and this is a threat.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I'm attached, basically, I am bound with that external, self-justifying, righteous point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: But this is the right thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not the right thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're finding safety in that external righteousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, you will find safety in the external authority, the external tradition.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, you found what nobody else understood on that external level.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, you are the right one.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if what you found safety is factually correct, say, it's the Buddha's words, the matter you took it in that external self-righteous sense, you haven't actually... Self-righteous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you haven't endured it internally on the right level.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why when the monks were falling out, almost they have a schism over like some vinaya rule about the salt or whatever it was.
[SPEAKER_02]: When the Buddha came, told them like, okay, you gotta stop this now, it's getting out of hand, and they sort of dismissed him three times.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, well, don't you worry about it, it's our karma, not your karma.
[SPEAKER_02]: They dismissed the person that defined the rule on account of which they feel self-righteous, and he tells them, you're both wrong now, and they dismiss him, because that's how intoxicating self-righteousness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: They dismissed the Buddha on account of...
[SPEAKER_02]: They're practicing the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: They became monks.
[SPEAKER_02]: He defined the rules.
[SPEAKER_02]: He tells them, okay, that's not important.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: You mind your own business, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how intoxicating it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even back then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it is rooted in that sense of safety, that sense of righteousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And obviously, for somebody who has been
[SPEAKER_02]: Already keeping the precepts in that manner of the external authority and then just redefining that righteousness, the clarity, to gain more righteousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, well, you know, I know Pali and I know the etymology of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I know Pali and I know the language before Pali.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I know the language before that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so I have the thread further than you.
[SPEAKER_02]: None of that... that's already a complete loss of context.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because is that where you find intentions?
[SPEAKER_02]: Your intentions for actions in dictionaries and languages and studying of etymologies?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's always going to be here and now.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's going to be the reason why you're looking at these places.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now that you're obviously unaware of.
[SPEAKER_02]: The reason you're unaware of.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yes, there needs to be some definition, some... that's what... eight precepts, ten precepts, that's... that's pretty much the kind of... the framework.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what covers the non... the... the actions that would... that would take you to centrality and ill-will and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't act towards those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything else, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you see a direct relation, direct benefit to taming the mind, you recognize it, but... and that's how you will not be dependent on anywhere in the world, even if they say, oh, none of these rules matter, or all these rules matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have a direct line to what matters, what's fault and what isn't fault, which is your own intentions, that you have been uprooting rightly, and not acting out of hindrances and doubt, and trying to get rid of them, and falling back onto the external authority for safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it is still the same external authority.
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody might turn to Ajahn, Ajahn says, that's my authority.
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody won't do that, for whatever personal preferences, but it will study the language upon language upon language upon language and discern the connections that nobody else seen, and that is my safety now.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, that is the unique thing there, that's clearly defined, inaccessible to doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Until somebody says, well, actually, that paper came later than what you think, and it's not before, but it was after.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're undermined.
[SPEAKER_02]: Already.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what do you do then?
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to revisit everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's only only a relative safety, because you placed it in a place, you put it in a place that's not actually safe, and can never be safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's kind of addictive as well, if you have found safety in that in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will be seeking in the same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's undermined.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, now I need to... Well, that's why Sīla Bhātparamāsa is one of the first three fetters.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a factual, real fetter.
[SPEAKER_02]: So...